<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godly exhortation made vnto the people of Antioch, by Iohn Chrysostome, sometime arch bishop of Constantinople: touching the patience and suffering affliction, by the examples of Iob, and the three children: and of refraining from swearing. Translated out of Latin into English, by Robert Rowse minister of the word of God</title>
            <author>John Chrysostom, Saint, d. 407.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04506</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14633</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107986</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843677</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843677</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8425</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04506)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8425)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 711:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godly exhortation made vnto the people of Antioch, by Iohn Chrysostome, sometime arch bishop of Constantinople: touching the patience and suffering affliction, by the examples of Iob, and the three children: and of refraining from swearing. Translated out of Latin into English, by Robert Rowse minister of the word of God</title>
                  <author>John Chrysostom, Saint, d. 407.</author>
                  <author>Rowse, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[56] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Creed,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Robert Rowse, from the original by John Chrysostom.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An exhortation to patience and suffring affliction.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A (-A1-2 and A7) B-D (-A8).</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, Greek --  5th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8425:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8425:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A GODLY EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HORTATION MADE vnto the people of <hi>Antioch,</hi> by <hi>Iohn Chryſoſtome,</hi> ſometime <hi>Arch-biſhop of</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople: Touching patience and ſuffering afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by the examples of <hi>Iob,</hi> and the three children: and of refraining <hi>from ſwearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of Latin into Engliſh, <hi>By</hi> Robert Rowſe <hi>Miniſter of the word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iam. 5. ver. 10, 11, 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Take, my brethren, the Prophets for an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample of ſuffring aduerſitie, and of long pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, which haue ſpoken in the name of the Lord. Behold, we count them bleſſed which endure, &amp;c. But before all things, my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ſweare not, neither by heauen, nor by earth, nor by any other oath, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by Thomas Creed, 1597.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8425:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8425:2"/>
            <head>To the right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull Sir <hi>Arthur Heueningham</hi> Knight, one of her Maieſties <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of Peace and Quorum, within</hi> the Counties of Norfolke and Suffolke, the continuance and increaſe both of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, and temporall bleſſings in this life: and after death, the ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable bleſſing of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worſhipfull: Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of late ſome occaſion, more then I did expert, for ſome ſmall time, to ſequeſter my minde, (as it were) from more ſerious ſtudies; I thought it good, for mine owne priuate exerciſe, to reade
<pb facs="tcp:8425:3"/>
ouer and peruſe certaine Sermons of the learned Father <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> among the which this Exhortation inſuing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fourth Sermon which hee prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at <hi>Antioch,</hi> is extant. VVhich I haue nowe for the benefite of others, tranſlated into Engliſh, the rather for the matter therein contained. For if it bee duly conſidered, and weighed with iudgement, we may ſee it is a moſt liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie mirrour, teaching all Chriſtians how to behaue themſelues in afflictions, to vſe patience in all manner of tribulations; to continue ſteadfaſt and vnmoueable in the fayth, and to holde fast the bleſſed hope of euerlaſting life. The occaſion that this godly father made this Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation vnto the people of <hi>Antioch,</hi> was this. The Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> and ſome of his predeceſſours, had cauſed certaine Monuments to bee ſet vppe at <hi>Antioch,</hi> for a memoriall of their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall dignitie, and royall magnificence.
<pb facs="tcp:8425:3"/>
And ſo it was that this Emperour had impoſed an hard Tribute vpon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſent his Letters to <hi>Antioch,</hi> commaunding the Inhabitants there, to make payment thereof. VVhereupon all the citizens were in ſuch perplexitie, and ſo ſore grieued, that a great number of them aſſembling togither, did greatlie murmure, and complaine, ſaying, that ſuch an intollerable Tribute was layde vpon them, that they were not able to beare it: and that they were vtterlie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done. This rumour being heard through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Citie, immediately a companie of the baſer ſort, vnruly and vnſtayd per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, made a tumult and ſedition in the Citie: and this ſeditious crew, to auenge themſelues, tooke vpon them in contempt of the Emperour, to deface, ſubuert, and ouerthrow the ſaid Monuments. VVhich enterpriſe being effected, they procured the great diſpleaſure of the Emperour. The Magistrates (as their loyall dutie
<pb facs="tcp:8425:4"/>
was) did preſently ſit in iudgement, to execute the Lawe vpon thoſe malefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours: and many of them being appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, were conuicted, and condemned to death. Some were cut off with the ſworde, ſome were burned, ſome were caſt vnto wilde beaſts to be deuoured, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the men, but alſo their children. The women beeing in miſerable perplexitie, ſeeing their husbands and children ledde away to be put to death, durst not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of their calamitie, for feare of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent daunger. Many of the men to ſaue themſelues, fled into deſart places. The reſt that remained in the Cittie, weighing the miſerable eſtate that they were in, by meanes of thoſe malignant offenders, diligently repayred to the Church to ſerue God in prayer, and to heare the worde of God preached, to their edification and comfort, in that moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous time, they kept a faſt. And at that inſtant <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> made this exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue
<pb facs="tcp:8425:4"/>
Sermon vnto them, beſides manie other Sermons, labouring what hee could to mooue the people to tranquillitie and peace, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort the minds of the afflicted; and to arme them with pacience, that they ſhould not bee diſmayed with the preſent troubles; conſidering that tribulation is ſent vnto the godly, for the triall of their faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that in the ende, the Lorde will giue a happie euent to all that constantly perſeuere in their godlie profeſsion, if they tarry the Lords leyſure; and depend vpon his prouidence, as at the length it come to paſſe vnto this people of <hi>Antioch.</hi> For after that <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> as a faithfull Paſtor had imployed much time and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in teaching them the good and right way, they being attentiue to heare him; it pleaſed God to giue ſuch a bleſsing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, that by his inſtancy in preaching, the wicked were ſtayed from attempting further euill; and the godly were great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly edified and confirmed in the faith. And
<pb facs="tcp:8425:5"/>
by the diſcreete wiſedome of <hi>Flauianus</hi> their Biſhop, who went as an Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour vnto the Emperour, in the name of the whole Cittie, to pacifie him, and to craue their pardon: where as before, the Emperour had threatned to ſubuert the Citie, and to deſtroy the inhabitants: the Lord turned his heart, ſo that he pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them, and hee and the Cittie were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, to the great ioy and comfort of them al. By this example of them of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> we may ſee, howe daungerous a thing it is, for Subiects to attempt any thing agaynſt their Prince, and the hurt that commeth of ſedition. Again, we may ſee, what great good redoundeth vnto the godlie, by the diligent preaching of pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Paſtors, who labor to bring the people vnto repentance, and amendment of life: and how the Lord doth bleſſe them, who being truely penitent for their ſinnes, doo vnfaignedlie turne vnto him, and are content to be reformed by the true Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers
<pb facs="tcp:8425:5"/>
of his worde. Although they ſuffer a great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>flict of tribulation &amp; afflictons yet the Lord in his good time, doth merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie deliuer them, mittigating their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, and turning their heauineſſe into ioy: wherby they haue most ample occaſion to render thankes vnto him, for his great goodneſſe and mercie extended towardes them. Now hauing finiſhed the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation hereof, and earnestly deſiring that ſome profite might thereby growe vnto others, to Gods glorie, and their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: I thought it not impertinent to publiſh it, and to preſent the ſame vnto your VVorſhip, as the first fruites of my labour in this kinde: the rather for that you are a zealous fauourer of the Goſpell, and true Religion establiſhed. If therefore your good worſhip ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in good part this my ſmall exerciſe, and ſhall vouchſafe to protect the ſame, I ſhall thinke my labour herein the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter imployed. And thus praying God
<pb facs="tcp:8425:6"/>
to continue his bleſsings towardes you, and long to preſerue you, for the further good and benefit of our Countrey: I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie take my leaue of your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. <hi>Stratton Michaell, 12. of October. 1597.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your worſhips moſt humble in the Lord,</hi> Robert Rowſe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8425:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A godlie Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taion made vnto the people of Antioch, by</hi> Iohn Chryſoſtome, <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time</hi> Archbiſhop of Conſtantinople: <hi>tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching patience and ſuffering affliction,</hi> by the examples of <hi>Iob,</hi> and the three children, and of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraining from ſwearing.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Leſſed bee God, who hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie ſoules; and ſtrengthned your wauering minds, for by this your care and readineſſe of hearing, yee haue ſhewed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you haue receiued agreeable conſolation. For it is not
<pb facs="tcp:8425:7"/>
commonlie graunted, that the ſoule beeing ſorrowfull and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed downe with the cloude of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe, can heare with readineſſe the thinges that are ſpoken. But I ſee you giuing heede vnto vs, with much fauour and earneſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, hauing ſhaken off all heauie cogitations, and that yee haue driuen awaye the inſtant an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh with the deſire of hearing. Therefore I thanke GOD, with you, that miſerie hath not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payred our Diſcipline, neither hath feare ſlacked our earneſtneſſe, nor tribulation quenched your fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentneſſe, nor the greatneſſe of daunger corrupted your zeale: neyther hath the feare of men o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome your deſire to Godward, nor the iniquitie of the time ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne your ſtudie. Not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye hath it not ouerthowne it, but
<pb facs="tcp:8425:7"/>
ſtayed it vppe as with winges; not onelie hath it not diminiſhed, but increaſed; not quenched, but more and more kindled your ſtudie. The common place of dayly aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, is emptie; but the Church is filled, the one is a matter of mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and lamentation; the other is an occaſion of ioy and ſpirituall gladneſſe. Therefore (beloued) when thou goeſt into the common place of vſuall meetings, and mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt becauſe thou ſeeſt no bodie there, flie vnto thy mother the Church,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.26.</note> and ſtreight-way ſhee will comfort thee with the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of her owne children: and ſhee will ſhewe thee a perfect and diuine companie of brethren, and will driue away all heauineſſe. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, wee dwelling as it were in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart places, doo deſire to ſee men in the Cittie; but fleeing vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:8425:8"/>
Church, we are preſſed with a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude. And as when the Sea floweth fiercely, and rageth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamelie with manie ſtormes, feare conſtraineth all men to flie vnto the hauen: ſo alſo at this inſtant, the ſtormes of Affliction in the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall place, and the winter that is in the Cittie, doo compell all men on euerie ſide to flie vnto the Church: and doo binde the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers togither among themſelues, with the bonde of Charitie. Let vs therefore giue thankes to God alſo for theſe benefites, that wee haue reaped ſuch commoditie by tribulation, and for that wee haue receyued ſo great profite by temptation. Except there bee temptation, there is no Crowne: except there bee conflicts, there be no rewards: without ſtudie, there is no honour; without tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:8425:8"/>
no mitigation of griefe; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Winter, no Sommer. And this wee may ſee, not onely in men, but in the verie ſeedes. For theſe it behooueth that there bee much raine, much breaking out of clouds, and laſtly much ice: if the ſprow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting eare ſhall kindlie ſpring vppe, and when ſeede tyme is, then alſo is the time of raine.</p>
            <p>Seeing then that nowe in like manner the Winter of our ſoules and not of the Ayre, is imminent; Let vs alſo ſowe in this VVinter, that wee may reape in Sommer; Let vs ſowe teares, that wee may reape ioye. This is not my ſpeech,<note place="margin">Pſal. 126.6</note> but the denunciation of the Prophette. <hi>They that ſowe in Teares, ſhall reape in ioy.</hi> A ſhower of raine falling, dooth not make the Seedes ſo to braunch and growe vppe, as the ſhower of
<pb facs="tcp:8425:9"/>
teares that falleth dooth ſtirre vppe thee ſeede of godlineſſe, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it to ſpreade foorth his braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
            <p>This ſhower cleanſeth the ſoule, watereth the minde, and cauſeth the braunches of doctrine in ſhort time to come forth. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is needfull to cut a deepe furrowe, for ſo alſo hath the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet admoniſhed vs,<note place="margin">Iere. 4.</note> ſaying: <hi>Breake vppe your fallowe grounde, and ſowe not among Thornes.</hi> Therefore, as hee that ſetteth in the Plough downewarde, openeth the earth, preparing a ſafe keeping for the ſeedes, leaſt when they be throwne abroade, they ſhoulde remaine on the vppermoſt parte of the grounde: but that they ſhould bee conueyed into the verie boſome of the earth, and ſafelie take roote: ſo alſo it is neceſſarie for vs to doo,
<pb facs="tcp:8425:9"/>
and vſing tribulation as a Plough, to cutte vnto the bottome of the heart. For this dooth another Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phette admoniſh vs, ſaying;<note place="margin">Ioel. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Rent your hearts, and not your Garments.</hi> Let vs therefore rent our heartes: ſo that if there bee any deceyua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble weede, and wicked cogitation in vs, wee may pull it vppe by the roote, and make our grounde pure and cleane with the Seedes of godlineſſe: For except wee nowe make readie our ground, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept wee ſow now, except we now powre foorth teares, when tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and faſting is preſent; when ſhall wee euer come to haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction of heart? Shall we haue it in the time of eaſe and pleaſure? But that can not bee. For eaſe and pleaſure are woont to bring men into ſlouthfulneſſe; as tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is the meane to drawe men
<pb facs="tcp:8425:10"/>
vnto ſtudy, and to conuert the mind which wandereth, and is outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly occupied about many things. Therefore let vs not be greeued at this dolefull ſadneſſe, but let vs giue thanks vnto God, for of tribulation commeth much gaine. For when the husbandman alſo ſoweth the ſeedes that hee with much labour hath gathered together: one that is ignorant and without skill will wonder at it, and perhaps will ſay within himſelf, what doth this man now at the laſt? he ſcattereth abroad the ſeedes which he hath gathered together, neither doth hee ſcatter them onely, but doth mingle them in the earth with much care, that they cannot eaſily bee gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Neither doth hee onelie mixt them with the earth, but alſo hee wiſheth that a great raine may come, that all the ſeeds that he hath
<pb facs="tcp:8425:10"/>
caſt abroad may putrifie &amp; become as clay: and this man ſeeing the lightnings and glitterings appeare, wil be troubled and diſmaid. But as for the husbandman it is not ſo with him, but he reioyceth and is glad, when he beholdeth the winter: for he reſpecteth not the things preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but he beholdeth the things that are to come: he hath no reſpect to the lightnings, but hee counteth his ſheafes: he reſpecteth not the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifying ſeedes, but the ſpringing eares of corne: he regardeth not the great ſhowers, but the pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowing of his corn vpon the floor. In like manner let vs behold not the preſent tribulation or ſorrow, but the profitte that ſpringeth of it, and the fruite that groweth of it: let vs expect the ſtore cheſt and the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulles. For if wee be vigilant, wee may gather of this time much fruit,
<pb facs="tcp:8425:11"/>
and may fill the ſtore-houſe of our mind. If wee watch, wee ſhall not onely ſuffer no grieuance, but alſo we ſhall receiue innumerable ſtore of good things: but if wee be ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſlackneſſe and reſt will ſpoyle vs. For both watchfulneſſe and reſt do hurt him that taketh no heede to his conuerſation: but to him that with diligent care directeth his life aright, they are both profitable. And as gold although it remaine in the water, doth yet ſhew his appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant hue, or if it fal into the furnace, it appeareth again more bright: but clay and graſſe if it happen them to be mixed in the water, the one rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and the other is diſſolued: or if the one falleth into the fire, it is dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the other is burnt: ſo alſo it is with the righteous man and the ſinner: the righteous man whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee enioy reſt, remayneth
<pb facs="tcp:8425:11"/>
bright and cleare, as gold drenched in the water: or whether hee fall by temptation, hee becommeth more bright, euen as gold tryed in the fire. But the ſinfull man, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he obtain eaſe, is diſſolued and conſumed as the graſſe and clay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding in the water: or whether he ſuffer temptation hee is burnt vp and deſtroyed as the clay and graſſe in the fire. Let vs not therefore bee conſumed with the preſent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, for if thou haſt commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſinnes, they are deſtroyed and eaſily burnt vppe by tribulation: but if thou haſt vertue, thou art lightened and made bright by the ſame. If thou watch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually and bee ſober, thou ſhalt ouercome all euill. For not the nature of temptations, but the ſluggiſhnes of them that are temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is wont to cauſe the ruine.
<pb facs="tcp:8425:12"/>
Therefore, if thou wilt bee glad, and enioy both eaſe and pleaſure, neither ſeeke pleaſure nor eaſe, but ſeeke to haue thy ſoule full of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tince, &amp; able to indure and ſuffer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions. If thou haſt not this gift, temptation ſhall not only conuince thee, but alſo eaſe ſhall deſtroy thee, and caſt thee downe the more. And that not the inuaſion of gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous caſualties, but the vntoward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our minds doth ſubuert our ſaluation: heare what Chriſt ſayth: <hi>VVhoſoeuer heareth of mee theſe words, and dooth them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.24.25.26.27</note> 
               <hi>ſhall be likened vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a wiſe man, which hath builded his houſe vpon a Rocke, and the raine fell, and the flouds came, and the winds blew, and beate vppon that houſe, and it fell not, for it was grounded vpon a Rocke. But euerie one that heareth theſe my wordes, and doth them not, ſhall bee likened vnto a fooliſh man, which hath
<pb facs="tcp:8425:12"/>
builded his houſe vppon the Sand, and the raine fell, and the flouds came, and the winds blew, and beate vppon that Houſe, and it fell, and the fall thereof was great.</hi> Thou ſeeſt that not the aſſaults of temptations, but the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe of the Builders cauſed the ruine: for there was raine, and here raine: there were floudes, and heere were flouds, and there was inuaſion of windes, and heere was the like: And that man buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and this man builded, and the building was all one, and the tryalles all one, but they had not all one ende, becauſe they had not both one foundation. For the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the tryalles cauſed not the fall, but the follie of the builder: or elſe the Houſe that was buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vppon the Rocke muſt alſo haue fallen: but nowe that Houſe ſuffered no ſuch ouerthrow. But
<pb facs="tcp:8425:13"/>
think not you that theſe things are ſpoken concerning a houſe, but the ſpeech is meant concerning the ſoule, which by workes either ſheweth or elſe reiecteth the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the word of God. So in like maner did <hi>Iob</hi> build his ſoule. <hi>The raine diſcended,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 1.</note> 
               <hi>for the fire fell from heauen, and conſumed all his heards of cattell.</hi> The flouds came, that is to ſay, often and continuall meſſengers without ceaſing, ſhewing him of his calamities, one telling him that his flocks of Cattel were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; another telling him of the death of his Children. The windes blewe, that is, the bitter wordes of his wife, Curſe GOD (ſayth ſhee) and die. And yet his houſe fell not, his ſoule was not vndermyned. This Righteous man did not blaſpheme, but gaue thankes vnto God, ſaying: <hi>The
<pb facs="tcp:8425:13"/>
Lorde gaue, and the Lorde hath taken away: euen as it pleaſed the Lord ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is it come to paſſe: bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi> Seeſt thou not that not the nature of temptations, but the ſlackneſſe of the ſlothfull is wont to cauſe the ouerthrow. Therefore tribulation maketh a man ſtronger and ſtronger. But who ſpeaketh this? the bleſſed Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> beeing nouriſhed in tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for thus hee ſayth: <hi>Tribulation bringeth foorth patience, and patience experience, and experience hope.</hi> And as the violence of windes happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and toſſing the ſtrong trees too and fro, doth not plucke them vp, but maketh them more ſtrong and firme by thoſe inuaſions: ſo in like maner do the aſſaults of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, not ouerthrow the ſoule that is holy and liueth godly, but alſo do prepare the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:8425:14"/>
vnto greater patience, as they made bleſſed <hi>Iob</hi> more famous &amp; renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. And now verily a man is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie with vs; a man ſubiect to the ſame puniſhments, and hauing the like ſoule, and we are afraied; but then the malignant and cruell Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell was angrie: neither was he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly angrie, but he practiſed all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of craftes, and applied all his ſubtiltie; and yet did hee not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the valiaunt ſtrength of this iuſt man. And the King indeed bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but a man, is now angrie, and ſoone after appeaſed, and yet wee are dead with feare: but then when <hi>Iob</hi> was aſſaulted, the Diuell beſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him, who is neuer reconciled to the nature of men: but hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced warre againſt our lynage, without any league, and battell without any truce: and yet this iuſt man ſcorned his arrowes, and had
<pb facs="tcp:8425:14"/>
them in contempt. What excuſe then, or what pardon ſhal we haue, which cannot beare the temptation of man: whereas hee being before the time of grace, and vnder the old Teſtament, did ſo valiantly beare that ſo intollerable a battell? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, beloued, let vs alwayes reaſon of theſe things among our ſelues, and let vs by theſe ſpeeches exhort our ſelues; for yee your ſelues are witneſſes, and our owne conſciences alſo, what great profit we haue had by this temptation and triall. For, by meanes hereof, the looſe liuer is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come modeſt: the bolde and ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous perſon is become more gentle: the ſlouthful perſon more ſtucious: they that neuer ſawe the Church, but ſpent whole daies in beholding playes vpon the ſtages, doo nowe abide all day in the Church. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bee not thou ſorie, that God
<pb facs="tcp:8425:15"/>
hath made thee ſtudious through feare; and that by tribulation he hath brought thee to the feeling of thy ſaluation. But is thy conſcience tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented? Is thy mind daily diſmaid, expecting death and great threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings? But hereby alſo ſhal we haue great acceſſe vnto vertue, while Religion increaſeth in vs by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh. For God is able this day to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe vs from all our heauie afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but vntill hee ſee vs pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, vntil he ſee our conuerſion ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, &amp; our repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce firme and ſtable, he will not diſſolue our tribulation. For the Goldſmith vntil he ſee the gold well purified, dooth not draw it out of the forge; ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe God will not remooue this cloud, vntill he hath fully amended vs. For he that hath ſuffered vs to be tempted, knoweth alſo the time to take away this temptation. And
<pb facs="tcp:8425:15"/>
as hee that playeth vpon a Harpe, neither ſtretcheth the ſtring too much, leaſt hee breake it, neither ſlacketh it out of meaſure, leaſt hee hurt the conſent of the harmonie: ſo likewiſe doth God, he appointeth our ſoules to be neither in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all reſt, nor yet in long tribulation, doing both theſe thinges according to his heauenly wiſedome: for hee ſuffereth vs not to enioy continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all eaſe, leaſt wee ſhoulde become more ſlouthfull: and againe, he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth vs not to bee in continuall trouble, leaſt we ſhould vtterlie fall or diſpaire. Therefore let vs leaue the time of releaſing our griefs vnto him, and let vs onely liue in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. For the work that we haue to do, is to be changed vnto vertue: but it is the worke of God to diſſolue aduerſities: for he hath a more ready will to quench this burning flame,
<pb facs="tcp:8425:16"/>
then thou thy ſelfe haſt, but he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecteth thy ſaluation. Therefore as tribulation commeth of eaſe, ſo alſo it is expedient, after trouble to look for eaſe, and mittigation of our griefes. For neither is it alway win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor alway ſommer, nor alway ſtormes, nor alway calme weather; nor alway night, nor alway day; ſo neither ſhall wee alway haue tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, but there ſhall bee a mittiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if we alway giue thankes vnto God in trouble.<note place="margin">Dan. 3</note> For the three chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were caſt into the burning O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: and yet for all that, they forgat not to ſtand in their Religion: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did the fire make them afrayed, but ſitting in the Fornace as in a Chamber, and feeling no greefe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing circumſpectly compaſſed bout with fire, they powred out thoſe holye prayers which they made. Therfore the fire became vnto them
<pb facs="tcp:8425:16"/>
as a wall, the flame a garment, and the ouen a fountane; and the fire receiuing them bound, made them looſe. It receiued their bodies which were mortall, and abſtained from them as if they had beene immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall: the fire knewe not his owne nature, but ſhewed reuerence vnto godlineſſe. The tyraunt bounde their feete, and their feete did ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the force of the fire. O won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull thing! the flame looſed them that were bound; and againe the flame was ouercome of them that were bound. For the religion of the yong men did change the nature of things. Yea verilie, it chaunged not nature it ſelfe, but that which was more wonderfull, it reſtrained the force of nature, which is permanent and durable. It que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched not the fire, but made it to bee without force, while it burned. And that which is
<pb facs="tcp:8425:17"/>
wonderfull, and may make vs aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied: this was not done only in their bodies which were holy: but alſo in their garments,<note place="margin">Act 9.11 12 Act. 5.15.16</note> and ſhooes. And as in the Apoſtles, the raiment of <hi>Paul</hi> did expel ſickneſſes, and diuels: and the ſhadow of <hi>Peter</hi> did driue away death: ſo likewiſe here, the ſhooes of the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quenched the power of the fire. I know not in what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner I ſhould declare it. The miracle exceedeth all declaration that can be, by wordes. For the force of the fire was quenched, and it was not quenched: for when it was occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodies of thoſe ſaints, it was quenched, and when it ſhuld breake their bonds in ſunder, it was not quenched: therefore it brake their fetters, and yet it touched not ſo much as their Ancles. Thou ſeeſt what a neare connection there was: neither was the fire
<pb facs="tcp:8425:17"/>
chaunged and depriued of his power, neither durſt it proceede to execute his power, beeing kept, as it were, within bondes. The ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant bound them, and the flame looſed them: that thou maiſt learne both what was the crueltie of that barbarous man, and alſo the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Element. But for what cauſe did he bind them to caſt them into the fire? That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miracle might be the greater, that the ſigne might bee the more wonderful, that thou ſhouldeſt not thincke, that the thinges which were ſeene, were a deceyuing of the eyes: for except that that fire had beene fire, it had not taken awaye their bondes: and (that which is a farre greater thing) it had not deuoured thoſe Souldiours which ſate without: But nowe the fire ſhewed his vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to thoſe that were without:
<pb facs="tcp:8425:18"/>
and obedience to thoſe who were within. But conſider thou with me in all reſpects, howe the diuell by what things he ſtriueth againſt the ſeruants of God, by the ſame things hee deſtroyeth his owne power: not willingly indeede, but the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and prouidence of God vſing his owne weapons and crafts vpon his owne head. Which thing alſo here came to paſſe. For the diuell then inſinuating himſelfe into that Tyrant, did neither permit that the heades of thoſe Saints ſhould be cut off with the ſworde, nor that they ſhould be giuen vnto beaſtes: nor that they ſhould be puniſhed by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſuch meanes: but he coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled him, that they ſhould bee caſt into the fire; to the ende that not ſo much as the reliques of thoſe Saints might remaine, their bodies being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed, &amp; the aſhes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mixed
<pb facs="tcp:8425:18"/>
with the aſhes of ſticks and fuell. But God vſed this meane to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the diuels wickedneſſe. And after the ſame maner (as I ſhall preſently declare) among the Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans the fire is ſuppoſed to bee God, &amp; the barbarous people alſo which do now inhabite that countrey, do worſhip the ſame with much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. God therfore willing vtterly to roote out this matter of vngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, graunted a moderation to this torment, to the end that hee might giue victorie vnto his ſeruants, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eyes of all them that truely worſhipped him: willing to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them by thoſe his works, that the Gods of the Gentiles doo not onely ſtand in feare of God, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo they feare the ſeruants of God. And conſider the Crowne of victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie formed by contraries, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies themſelues which were
<pb facs="tcp:8425:19"/>
made witneſſes of the victorie. For (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>Nabuchodonoſor</hi> the king ſent foorth to gather togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the nobles, the rulers &amp; dukes, the iudges, the Princes, the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers, and officers, and all the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of the prouinces, that they ſhould come to the dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the new image: &amp; they were all aſſembled together. The enemie compelleth the beholders, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> together to the ſight: he beſtoweth diligence, &amp; a Theater, not of common perſons, not of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine priuate men, but of all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and of all the Magiſtrates, that there might alſo bee witneſſe woorthie of credit among many. They that were called came to ſee one ſight, and when they behelde other ſights, they went all away. They came to worſhip the Image, and when they ſaw what had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened,
<pb facs="tcp:8425:19"/>
they ſcorned the Image, and departed wondering at the power of God, by the miracle ſhewed in theſe childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And behold where he had ſet this ſtage, not in the citie, nor in any ſeuerall coaſt, but the plaine and bare fields do receiue this The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ater of the world: for he ſet vp the Image in the field of <hi>Dura,</hi> without the Citie. And an Herald paſſed by, and cryed aloude, <hi>Be it knowne to you, O ye people, nations, and languages, that when ye heare the ſound of the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, pipe, &amp; harpe, the dulcimer, the pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery and ſimphonie, and al kind of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of muſicke, ye fall downe and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe the golden Image</hi> (for to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Image was to fall indeede) <hi>and whoſoeuer falleth not downe and worſhippeth, ſhall the ſame houre be caſt into a burning furnace of fire.</hi> Thou ſeeſt what hard conflicts were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, and how many neceſſities of
<pb facs="tcp:8425:20"/>
ſubtile practiſes they had, and what a deepe gulfe and downefall there was on both ſides. But be not thou afraide: for by how much more the enemie increaſed his craftie engins, by ſo much the more hee ſheweth the valiant courage of thoſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. For to this ende were there ſo many conſents of inſtruments of muſicke: and to this ende was the hot burning furnace, that both pleſure and feare might take place in the hearts of the ſtanders by. Is any man that ſtandeth by dumpiſh and vnpleaſant, ſayth the Tyrant? let the delightfull melodie of all kind of muſick mollifie him. Is any man of higher conceit then theſe ſubtile practiſes? let the ſight of the flaming fire terrifie him, and ſtrike him amazed. And inded there was both feare &amp; pleaſure: pleaſure pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uily entring into their eares, and
<pb facs="tcp:8425:20"/>
feare ſecretly pearcing through their eyes into their ſoules: but none of theſe things did daunt the noble courage of thoſe yong men: but as they were caſt into the fire, and did ouercome the flame, ſo they laughed to ſcorne all concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence and ſorrowfull perplexitie. For the diuell had prepared al theſe things for them: hee doubted not of the Subiects, but rather hee had much confidence that there was no man that would ſet himſelfe againſt the Kings law. And after that, they all fell downe and were ouercome: then theſe Children were brought forth alone into the middeſt of the throng, that ſo the victorie alſo might bee more famous: for that they among ſo great a multitude, ſhould get the victorie, and be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely extolled with commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Neither had it been ſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:8425:21"/>
a thing, if (when no man was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome) theſe yong men had been the firſt that had valiantly behaued themſelues: but this is the greateſt thing, and to be maruailed at, that the multitude of thoſe that fell downe, did not make them afraide nor diſcourage them. They ſayde not within themſelues any ſuch thing, as many are accuſtomed to ſay. If wee indeede ſhould bee the firſt that ſhould worſhippe the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, that ſhould be a ſinne in vs: but if wee doo this with ſo many thouſandes of people, who will not pardon vs? who will not iudge vs woorthie to bee excuſed? But they neyther ſpake nor thought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch thing, when they beheld the ouerthrowes of ſo many Ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rants. But conſider thou with me the malignant diſpoſition of thoſe that accuſed them, &amp; how lewdly
<pb facs="tcp:8425:21"/>
and howe bitterly they accuſed them. There bee (ſay they) certaine men which are Iewes, whom thou haſt ſet ouer the charge of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince of <hi>Babell:</hi> for they did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make mention of the Countrey, but alſo they called to minde their honour and dignitie: and that they might kindle the kings diſpleaſure againſt them, this they alleaged. Thou, O King, haſt made our prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as it were ſlanes, without any citie, and captiues: but theſe men do ſtaine with diſhonour, this ſo great honour, and do behaue themſelues proudly againſt him who hath ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced them vnto honor: therfore ſay they, theſe Iewes whom thou haſt ſette ouer the prouince of the countrey of <hi>Babell,</hi> haue not obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy decree, and they will not ſerue thy goddes. Their accuſation was a great commendation, and the crimes obiected againſt them doo
<pb facs="tcp:8425:22"/>
turne to their praiers, euen the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues bearing vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted record. But what doth the king? he commanded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bee brought forth into the middeſt of the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie, to the intent hee might terrifie them on euerie ſide. But yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing made them abaſhed: not the furie of the King: not becauſe they were left alone in the middeſt of ſo great potentates: not the ſight of the fire: not the noyſe of the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding: nor al they that did caſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the fire: but they laughing al theſe things to ſcorne, entred into the furnace, as if they had beene to be caſt into a cold ſpring of water: giuing out that bleſſed voyce; <hi>O King, wee will not ſerue thy Gods, nor worſhippe the golden Image which thou haſt ſet vp.</hi> I haue not vnaduiſedly recited this Hiſtorie, but to the ende that yee may learne, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:8425:22"/>
the king be now diſpleaſed and angrie with vs: although the men of warre do lay waite for vs, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the enuie of the enimies do afflict vs; though there bee captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and berefting of children, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there bee fire, although there be a furnace, and an innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſort of euils: yet nothing can diſmay or terrifie the righteous ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For if when there was a wicked King, theſe yong men did not feare the rage of the Tyrant, much more doth it behooue vs to bee of good comfort, hauing a gentle &amp; a meeke King, and to giue God thankes for this trouble, beeing taught by that which before hath beene ſpoken, that tribulations doo make vs more noble, both with God, and with our ſelues beeing men; knowing how to beare them valiantly. For if theſe yong men had not beene ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants,
<pb facs="tcp:8425:23"/>
we had not knowne their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie; if they had not bin captiues, we had not learned their nobleneſſe of minde. Except they had fallen from their countrey here beneath, we had not knowne their vertue to be from the heauenly Citie aboue: except the earthly king had beene angry with them, we had not heard of the good wil which the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly king did beare to them. Therfore if thou alſo haue him bountiful and kind vnto thee, although thou fall into a furnace, diſpayre not. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if he be angrie, although thou be in Paradiſe, preſume not. For <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> was in Paradiſe: and after that he prouoked God to wrath, Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe did nothing at all profitte him. Theſe young men were in the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, &amp; for that they behaued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues wel, the fire did not hurt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Adam</hi> was in Paradiſe, and becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:8425:23"/>
he was ſlothfull, hee was vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and deceiued. <hi>Iob</hi> ſate in the dung, and becauſe hee was watchfull, hee obtained the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: although without compariſon, Paradiſe was the better &amp; more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent place. But the vertue of the place did nothing profit him that dwelt in it, after that hee had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed himſelfe: as alſo the vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the place did not hurt him, that was fortified on euerie ſide with vertue. Lette vs alſo likewiſe arme our ſelues with vertue: For whether the penaltie of our money be inflicted vppon vs, or whether death be imminent, yet no man can take away godlineſſe: and hauing that, we are more happie then all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. For this hath Chriſt alſo commaunded vs, ſaying;<note place="margin">Mat. 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>Be ye wiſe therefore as ſerpents.</hi> For as the ſerpent thruſteth foorth the other partes of
<pb facs="tcp:8425:24"/>
his body, that hee may ſaue his head: ſo likewiſe do thou, whether thou be to looſe thy money, or thy bodie, or this preſent life, or all things beſide, to the ende that thou maiſt preſerue godlineſſe: bee not ſorrowfull, for if thou depart hence hauing godlineſſe, God will render again al things vnto thee with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter excellencie: he wil both reſtore thy bodie againe with greater glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and in ſteede of thy money hee wil giue thee ſuch goods, as do ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount all the power of reaſon to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme of. For <hi>Iob</hi> ſate naked vppon the dung-hill, leading a life more greeuous the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a number of deaths: but becauſe hee reiected not godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, all his goods which he had at the firſt, were reſtored vnto him with greater abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance: the health and comely hue of his bodie, the whole companie of his children,
<pb facs="tcp:8425:24"/>
and al his poſſeſſions; &amp; that which is the greateſt thing of all, the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous crowne of patience was giuen vnto him. For as it happeneth in trees, if a man take away the fruit with the leaues, and cut off all the boughs, yet if the roote remaineth, the whole tree ſpringeth vp againe with greater comlineſſe. So is it alſo with vs, if the roote of godlineſſe remaine in vs, though our riches be taken away, and our bodies corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or deſtroyed; yet all things ſhall returne againe vnto vs with greater glorie. Therefore caſting away all ſorrowfull anguiſh of the ſoule, and ſuperfluous care, let vs returne again vnto our ſelues: let vs garniſh our bodyes and ſoules with the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of vertue, making the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of our bodies weapons of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and not of ſinne. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all things, lette vs teach our
<pb facs="tcp:8425:25"/>
tongue to bee the miniſter of grace, putting away out of our mouths all poyſoned and malitious ſpeech, and the meditation of filthie words. For by the grace of God aſſiſting vs, we may make euerie one of our mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers inſtruments of righteouſneſſe: as they whom grace do not preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, do make their members inſtruments of wickednes. Heare therfore how ſome haue made their tongues wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of ſinne, and how ſome haue made them weapons of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith of ſome,<note place="margin">Pſal. 57.5. Pſal. 45.2.</note> 
               <hi>Their tongue is a ſharpe ſword:</hi> but of himſelfe he ſaith, <hi>My tongue is the pen of a readie writer.</hi> The tongue of the one wrote death: the other did write the law of God. Therfore the tongue of the one was a ſword, and the tongue of the other a penne: not in reſpect of their owne nature, but in regarde of the diſpoſition of
<pb facs="tcp:8425:25"/>
thoſe that vſed them. For the nature of the tongue both of the one party and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, was all one, but they had not both one operation. And again, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like we may ſee concerning the mouth, for ſome had their mouth full of filthie corruption and wickednes, therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing them, ſaid,<note place="margin">Pſal. 10.7.</note> 
               <hi>Their mouth is full of curſing &amp; bitternes.</hi> But his mouth was otherwiſe inclined:<note place="margin">Pſal 49.3.</note> therfore he ſaith, <hi>My mouth ſhal ſpeake of wiſedom, and my hart ſhal muſe of vnderſtanding.</hi> Again, ſome had hands full of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, &amp; blaming the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaid, <hi>Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie is in their hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 26.10:</note> 
               <hi>and their right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is ful of gifts:</hi> but he had his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds cheifly accuſtomed to nothing elſe, but to be lifted vp toward heauen: and therfore he alſo ſpeaking of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 141.2.</note> 
               <hi>Let the lifting vp of my hands be an euening ſacrifice.</hi> And the like we may ſee in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart, for their hart was vain,
<pb facs="tcp:8425:26"/>
but his heart was true and vpright. Therefore hee ſaith of them,<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.9. Pſal. 45.1.</note> 
               <hi>Their heart is foule and vain:</hi> but of his own heart he ſaith, <hi>My heart is inditing of a good matter.</hi> And againe a man may ſee the like example concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the hearing, for ſome had ſuch a kinde of hearing as beaſtes haue: that is to ſay, a fierce and impatient hearing: and reproouing them hee ſaith.<note place="margin">Pſal. 58.4.</note> 
               <hi>They are like the deafe Adder that ſtoppeth her eares.</hi> But his hearing was a receptacle of the words of God, and this he declared, ſaying: <hi>I will incline mine eare vnto the Parable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.4.</note> 
               <hi>and ſhew my darke ſpeech vpon the harp.</hi> Therfore ſeeing that we know theſe things, let vs arme our ſelues on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie ſide with vertue, &amp; ſo we ſhal eſcape the wrath of God. And lette vs make our bodily members wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of righteouſneſſe, and let vs teach our eyes, and our mouthes,
<pb facs="tcp:8425:26"/>
and our hands, and our feete, &amp; our heart, and our tongue, and all our body to bee conformable vnto ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. And let vs reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber thoſe three precepts, whereof I ſpake vnto you in the former Sermon, deſiring you that yee beare enimitie to no man, neither ſpeak ye euil of any of them that haue cauſed your ſorrow; and that yee would putte away that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly cuſtome of ſwearing out of your mouths. And of theſe two firſt precepts, we ſhall intreate at an other time: but all this preſent weeke, wee will ſpeake vnto you as touching ſwearing, beginning at the eaſier precept. For it is no labor to ouercome the cuſtome of vaine oathes, if we would beſtow but a little ſtudie, one of vs to exhort ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to aduertiſe and marke one another, requiring an account of our ſelues, and rehearſing the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments
<pb facs="tcp:8425:27"/>
that we deſerue, for the the things which wee haue forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to obſerue. For I pray you what ſhall the abſtinence from meates profit vs, except we expell the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked cuſtomes of the minde? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, wee haue nowe paſſed this whole day in faſting, in the euening therefore let vs ſet foorth our table: not like as it was yeſterday, but lette our diet be changed, and more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate. Can any of vs now ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this day hee hath changed his life, as he hath changed his table? that he hath changed his wicked cuſtome of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as hee hath changed his diet? elſe what ſhall our faſting profit vs? Therefore I exhort you, and ceaſe not to exhort you, that ye take eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſeuerall precept by it ſelfe, &amp; dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently beſtow two or three daies in performing the ſame: and ſo to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede and per ſeuere in obedience.
<pb facs="tcp:8425:27"/>
And as there bee ſome that enuie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in faſting, &amp; doo wonderfully co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tend about abſtaining fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meats: and ſome do paſſe two whole daies faſting, and other ſome excluding from their table, not only the vſe of wine &amp; oyle, but alſo euerie kind of diſh, do paſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole time of Lent, vſing only bread and water: ſo let vs alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tend, to chaſe away the hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhowers of ſwearing, and to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh that vngodly cuſtome from vs: for this is more profitable then al fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting: this is more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious then al ſtraightneſſe of liuing. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> care that we haue about abſtaining from meates, lette vs employ it about re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraining from ſwearing: for we ſhall incur the crime of extreme follie, if wee haue no regard to ſhunne the things that are forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, &amp; apply al our ſtudy about things indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For to eate our meate is a thing not forbidden: but to ſwear we are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden.
<pb facs="tcp:8425:28"/>
Dare we the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abſtaining from things gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, commit things that are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden? Therefore of charitie I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort you, to make ſome change of your euill life, &amp; vpon this exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſhew a beginning hereof in yourſelues. For if wee ſhall accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh this preſent faſt with ſo great care, putting this in effect, namely that this weeke we wil not ſweare, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weeke next inſuing, to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh wrath and enuie, &amp; the next week after, vtterly to root out back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting and euill ſpeaking, and then after that, amending other faults &amp; abuſes: ſo going forward the right way, we ſhall by little &amp; little come to the high degree of vertue, &amp; ſhal eſcape this preſent danger, and ſhall pacifie the Lord our God: and the multitude ſhal come againe vnto vs into the Citie. And then wee ſhall teach them that are fallen away by
<pb facs="tcp:8425:28"/>
flying, to committe the hope of our ſafetie, not to any ſtrong muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of places, nor to any vaine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge or flying away, but vnto god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines of mind, good diſpoſition, and vertuous inclination. And thus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting our liues in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of God, we ſhall both enioy theſe temporal good things, and alſo thoſe eternall and vnſpeakeable ioyes of heauen. Of the which ioyes, God grant that wee all may be made woorthie, by the grace and bountifulneſſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: by whom, and with whom, all glorie, honour, and power, be aſcribed vnto the father, with the moſt holy quickning and coeternal ſpirit, now and for euermore, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
